Last Updated: March 26, 2020

# JOSHUA S. SPEAGLE

Harvard University Department of Astronomy joshspeagle.github.io | jspeagle@cfa.harvard.edu

### RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests lie in the interdisciplinary fields of **astrostatistics** and **data science** at the intersections of astronomy, statistics, and computer science. I focus on developing new statistics and machine learning techniques to study **stars, galaxies, and other astronomical phenomena** using large datasets in order to better understand how galaxies like our own Milky Way evolve.

### **POSITIONS**

Banting Postdoctoral Fellow: University of Toronto	2020-2022
Project Academic Support Staff: Kavli IPMU, University of Tokyo	2015-2016

### **EDUCATION**

Harvard University: PhD in Astronomy	2016-2020
Advisers: Doug Finkbeiner, Charlie Conroy, and Daniel Eisenstein (with Alyssa Goodman)	
Harvard University: MA in Astronomy	2016-2020
Harvard University: BA in Astrophysics and Physics	2011-2015

### **AWARDS & HONORS**

Banting Postdoctoral Fellowship	2020
Department of Astronomy Teaching Award (Harvard)	Spring 2018
Certificate of Distinction in Teaching (Harvard)	Spring 2017, 2018; Fall 2018
National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship	2016

### **TEACHING**

I have a strong interest in undergraduate and graduate education and pedagogy, with a focus on skills such as **programming**, **statistics**, **and data science** that are invaluable across a wide range of disciplines but too often not taught as part of a typical science curriculum.

# **Harvard**: Teaching Fellow

ASTRON 22: The Unity of Science: From the Big Bang to the Brontosaurus and Beyond	Spring 2020
ASTRON 191: Astrophysics Laboratory	Spring 2019
ASTRON 17: Galactic and Extragalactic Astronomy	Fall 2018
ASTRON 130: Cosmology	Spring 2018
ASTRON 16: Stellar and Planetary Astronomy	Spring 2017

## Banneker Institute (Harvard): Course Instructor

Introduction to Programming in Python Summer 2017, 18, 19

### **PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES**

CfA Machine Learning Journal Club: Founder and Organizer

Manuscript Referee: ApJ, ApJL, AJ, A&A, MNRAS

2017-2020

2014-present

### **RECENT PRESENTATIONS**

Villanova: Colloquium

October 2019

Exploring the Galaxy Near and Far in the Age of Gaia

Harvard: Summer Colloquium (joint with Catherine Zucker)

June 2019

Charting Nearby Molecular Clouds with Gaia: A New Map of Our Local Interstellar Medium

GitHub Satellite 2019: Keynote Address Participant

May 2019

Invited for open source code contributions (dynesty) in the analysis of the supermassive black hole in M87 by the Even Horizon Telescope collaboration

Cambridge: Data Intensive Science Seminar

April 2019

Mapping the 3-D Distribution of Dust in the Milky Way with Stellar Photometry

Harvard: CMSA Big Data Conference

August 2018

Revealing the Milky Way's Dust-iny

Bayes Comp 2018: Poster

March 2018

Dynamic Nested Sampling with dynesty

UMass Amherst: Data Science Tea

October 2017

Big Data Inference: Combining Hierarchical Bayes and Machine Learning to Improve Photometric Redshifts

### **PUBLICATIONS**

I am an author of **35 papers**, including **10 as (co-)first author** (in **red**) and **13 where I have made substantial contributions** (in **blue**). These papers have over **1800 citations** (<u>h-index=17</u>), including over **650 citations** (<u>h-index=7</u>) for papers where I am (co-)first author.

My papers can be found online on <u>arxiv</u> and <u>ADS</u>.

# In Preparation

**37.** Speagle, J. S.; Zucker, C.; Cargile, P. A.; Bonaca, A.; Johnson, B. D.; Beane, A.; Kamdar, H.; Dotter, A.; Conroy, C.; Green, G. M.; Schlafly, E. F.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; Rix, H.-W.; & Goodman, A.

Mapping the Milky Way in 5-D with 120 Million Stars at High Galactic Latitudes

**Speagle, J. S.**; Zucker, C.; Cargile, P. A.; Johnson, B. D.; Beane, G.; Green, G. M.; Schlafly, E. F.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; Dotter, A.; Bonaca, A.; Conroy, C.; Rix, H.-W.; Goodman, A. A.; & Eisenstein, D. J.

Deriving Stellar Properties, Distances, and Reddenings from Photometry and Astrometry with brutus

#### Submitted

35. Cabrera-Ziri, I.; Speagle, J. S.; Dalessandro, E.; Usher, C.; Bastian, N. J.; Salaris, M.; Martocchia, S.; Kozhurina-Platais, V.; Niederhofer, F.; Lardo, C.; & Larsen, S. S., MNRAS

#### 2020

- 34. Bonaca, A.; Conroy, C.; Hogg, D. W.; Cargile, P. A.; Caldwell, N.; Naidu, R. P.; Price-Whelan, A. M.; **Speagle, J. S.**; & Johnson, B. D., **ApJL**High-Resolution Spectroscopy of the GD-1 Stellar Stream Localizes the Perturber Near the Orbital Plane of Sagittarius
- 33. Leja, J.; Speagle, J. S.; Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; van Dokkum, P.; & Franx, M., ApJ A New Census of the 0.2 < z < 3.0 Universe, Part I: The Stellar Mass Function
- **32. Portillo, S. K. N. & Speagle, J. S.**; & Finkbeiner, D. P., **AJ** *Photometric Biases in Modern Surveys*
- 31. Speagle, J. S., MNRAS

  dynesty: A Dynamic Nested Sampling Package for Estimating Bayesian Posteriors and Evidences
- 30. Alves, J.; Zucker, C.; Goodman, A. A.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Meingast, S.; Robitaille, T.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; Schlafly, E. F.; & Green, G. M., **Nature**Discovery of a Galactic-scale gas wave in the Solar Neighborhood **Press:** Official Website
- 29. Zucker, C.; Speagle, J. S.; Schlafly, E. F.; Green, G. M.; Finkbeiner, D. P., Goodman, A.; & Alves, J., A&A

  A Compendium of Distances to Molecular Clouds in the Star Formation Handbook

#### 2019

- 28. Speagle, J. S., arxiv

  A Conceptual Introduction to Markov Chain Monte Carlo Methods
- 27. Green, G. M.; Schlafly, E. F.; Zucker, C.; Speagle, J. S.; & Finkbeiner, D. P., ApJ A 3D Dust Map Based on Gaia, Pan-STARRS 1 and 2MASS
- 26. Huang, S.; Leauthaud, A.; Hearin, A.; Behroozi, P.; Bradshaw, C.; Ardila, F.; **Speagle, J.**; Tenenti, A.; Bundy, K.; Greene, J.; Sifón, C.; & Bahcall, N., **MNRAS**Weak Lensing Reveals a Tight Connection Between Dark Matter Halo Mass and the Distribution of Stellar Mass in Massive Galaxies
- **25. Speagle, J. S.**; Leauthaud, A.; Huang, S.; Bradshaw, C. P.; Ardila, F.; Capak, P. L.; Eisenstein, D. J.; Masters, D. C.; Mandelbaum, R.; More, S.; Simet, M.; & Sifón, C., **MNRAS** *Galaxy-Galaxy Lensing in HSC: Validation Tests and the Impact of Heterogeneous Spectroscopic Training Sets*
- 24. Namikawa, T. **et al.** [73 additional co-authors], **ApJ**Evidence for the Cross-correlation between Cosmic Microwave Background Polarization Lensing from POLARBEAR and the Cosmic Shear from Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam
- 23. Forbes, J. C.; Krumholz, M. R.; & **Speagle, J. S.**, **MNRAS**Towards a Radially-Resolved Semi-Analytic Model for the Evolution of Disc Galaxies Tuned with Machine Learning
- 22. Cook, B. A.; Conroy, C.; van Dokkum, P.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ

- Measuring Star-Formation Histories, Distances, and Metallicities with Pixel Color-Magnitude Diagrams I: Model Definition and Mock Tests
- 21. Safarzadeh, M.; Berger, E.; Leja, J.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJL

  Measuring the Delay Time Distribution of Binary Neutron Stars III. Using the Individual Star

  Formation Histories of Gravitational Wave Event Host Galaxies in the Local Universe

  Press: AAS NOVA
- 20. Hikage, C. et al. [35 additional co-authors], PASJ

  Cosmology from cosmic shear power spectra with Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam first-year data
- 19. Leja, J.; Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; van Dokkum, P.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Brammer, G.; Momcheva, I.; Skelton, R.; Whitaker, K. E.; Franx, M; & Nelson, E. J., **ApJ**An Older, More Quiescent Universe from Panchromatic SED Fitting of the 3D-HST Survey
- **18. Zucker, C. & Speagle, J. S.**; Schlafly, E. F.; Green, G. M., Finkbeiner, D. P.; Goodman, A. A.; & Alves, J., **ApJ**A Large Catalog of Accurate Distances to Local Molecular Clouds: The Gaia DR2 Edition
- 17. Leja, J.; Carnall, A. C.; Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ How to Measure Galaxy Star Formation Histories II: Nonparametric Models

#### 2018

- Zucker, C.; Schlafly E. F.; Speagle, J. S.; Green, G. M.; Portillo, S. K. N.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; & Goodman, A. A., ApJ
  A New Technique for Mapping Distances Across the Perseus Molecular Cloud Using CO Observations and Stellar Photometry
- 15. Medezinski, E.; Oguri, M.; Nishizawa, A.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Miyatake, H.; Umetsu, K.; Leauthaud, A.; Murata, R.; Mandelbaum, R.; Sifón, C.; Strauss, M. A.; Huang, S.; Simet, M.; Okabe, N.; Tanaka, M.; & Yutaka, K., **PASJ**Source Selection for Cluster Weak Lensing Measurements in the Hyper Sprime-Cam Survey
- 14. Oguri, M. **et al.** [24 additional co-authors], **PASJ**An optically-selected cluster catalog at redshift 0.1<z<1.1 from Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic Program S16A data
- 13. Mandelbaum, R. et al. [30 additional co-authors], PASJ

  The first-year shear catalog of the Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam SSP Survey
- 12. Tanaka, M.; Coupon, J.; Hsieh, B.-C.; Mineo, S., Nishizawa, A. J.; **Speagle, J.**; Furusawa, H.; Miyazaki, S.; & Murayama, H., **PASJ**Photometric Redshifts for the Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic Program Data Release 1
- 11. Aihara, H. et al. [108 additional co-authors], PASJ

  First Data Release of the Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic Program
- 10. Aihara, H. et al. [142 additional co-authors], PASJ

  The Hyper Suprime-Cam SSP Survey: Overview and Survey Design

- 9. Speagle, J. S. & Eisenstein, D. J., MNRAS

  Deriving Photometric Redshifts with Fuzzy Archetypes and Self-Organizing Maps II. Implementation
- 8. Speagle, J. S. & Eisenstein, D. J., MNRAS

  Deriving Photometric Redshifts with Fuzzy Archetypes and Self-Organizing Maps I. Methodology

#### 2016

- 7. Speagle, J. S.; Capak, P. L.; Eisenstein, D. J.; Masters, D. C.; Steinhardt, C. L., MNRAS

  Exploring Photometric Redshifts as an Optimization Problem: An Ensemble MCMC and Simulated

  Annealing-Driven Template-fitting Approach
- 6. Steinhardt, C. L.; Capak, P. L.; Masters, D. C.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ The Impossibly Early Galaxy Problem

#### 2015

5. Masters, D. C. et al. [19 additional co-authors], ApJ

Mapping the Galaxy Color-Redshift Relation: Optimal Photometric Redshift Calibration Strategies for Cosmology Surveys

#### 2014

- 4. Steinhardt, C. L. & Speagle, J. S., ApJ

  A Uniform History for Galaxy Evolution
- 3. Steinhardt, C. L.; **Speagle, J. S.** et al. [22 additional co-authors], **ApJL**Star Formation at 4 < z < 6 from the Spitzer Large Area Survey with Hyper-Suprime-Cam

  (SPLASH) **Press:** [PL]
- 2. Speagle, J. S.; Steinhardt, C. L.; Capak, P. L.; & Silverman, J. D., ApJS

  A Highly Consistent Framework for the Evolution of the Star-Forming 'Main Sequence' from z~0-6

#### 2011

1. Speagle, J. S.; Kaplan, D. L.; & van Kerkwijk, M. H., ApJ The X-ray Counterpart of the High-B Pulsar J0726-2612